SQL. It's more than an
injection outta here.
It's the love language of
our databases. You know,
the massive Excel spreadsheets
that run the world.
You need to learn SQL probably right now,
especially if you want
this job or this job,
or this job are pretty much any job in it.
And it's a skill I've actually had to use
a lot, almost too much, too much more.
My comfort. Cameron, have
you had to use SQL? Yeah.
Whenever I was a AWS cloud engineer,
I dealt with databases all the time.
So whether you're an aspiring hacker
looking to do some SQL injections,
get outta here,
or you're a cloud engineer wanting
to query all your qualms away.
See that 10 times fast query all your
qualms away query. I can't do it one time,
two times. Oh my gosh.
This is definitely a skill you want
to add to your toolbox right now.
Now before you freak out,
we're not going too deep here.
You don't need to become a SQL expert
unless you wanna become a DBA or
something. You pour brave, stupid soul,
but you're making bank and you're rich.
But knowing the basics like, Hey,
what even is a database that goes a long
way in pretty much every area of it.
So in this video, I'm
going to teach you SQL,
not too much like a
Goldilocks amount of sequel,
just enough to make you
dangerous, but not too dangerous.
I don't want you dropping elbows
on some poor unsuspecting tables.
So by the end of this video, you
will know how to create your own,
my sequel or my SQL database.
And you're gonna add some stuff into it
or remove some stuff, query some things.
So get your coffee ready. Mine is
right here and let's learn some sequel.
Now while you're sipping that
coffee, getting all fueled up,
ready to go to learn some sequel.
Let me tell you a scary story.
Did you know that your usernames and your
passwords they're often stored inside
a sequel database and sometimes
these databases spring a leak,
spilling your username and password
all over the dark web David Bumble.
I'm disappointed. You
gotta protect yourself.
This is where our sponsor
Dashlane comes in.
Dashlane does a great job at protecting
you from yourself. Come on John Hammond.
I love their password health feature,
which obviously I got some work to do.
I got 28 compromised passwords and
two weak ones, no weakness allowed.
And I also love their dark web monitoring,
cuz I wasn't kidding these databases
full of your passwords and emails and all
kinds of stuff. Get hacked and
leaked all the time in the dark web.
They monitor that stuff for
you. And they'll tell you, Hey,
change your day and password.
And then right here is my
favorite feature of Dashlane.
It's got two factor built right into it.
So it'll log into network Chuck academy.
I've got my security code right here.
Oh, don't copy that.
Nah, it's gonna change.
So I pretty much use Dashlane for
everything, including my business.
I force all of my employees to
use Dashlane cuz they're crazy.
And they still write their passwords
down on post-it notes. Come on.
So if you have a business use Dashlane,
they've got a great admin section,
little admin console where you can manage
all your passwords for your employees.
Gotta keep them suckers in line.
And it's not just passwords.
You can put secure notes. You
can put your payments in here.
I use this all the time. It makes
paying for things so much easier.
So don't let someone else's
bad database put you at risk.
Get yourself the password manager.
I recommend Dashlane go out to
dashlane.com/network Chuck 50.
And you do get a discount. Let me double
check what that is. I forgot. Oh sweet.
You get 50% off. So use that code.
You can use it on pretty much any device
you have, which I do on every device.
Thank you to Dashlane for sponsoring
this video. Now let's get back to SQL.
Here we go. So SQL or SQL,
it stands for structured query language.
Focus on that term language because it
is kind of like a programming language,
similar to Python, except the primary
use of SQL is to talk to databases.
I told you it's their love language.
They love it. That's my database.
By the way, I'm gonna label
it using this query language.
We'll talk to our database. We'll
create things. We'll read things.
We'll update things. We'll delete
things. Crud. You've heard a crud, right?
Well you just did. So here we go. We are
gonna learn some sequel here in a bit.
But first let's talk about what's a
database I joked earlier how it's just one
big giant Excel spreadsheet.
That's kind of true.
You've probably seen an Excel
spreadsheet before, right?
It has columns or fields.
It has rows or we might call those records
and these rows or records contain our
data. And while Excel might work
for carrying the accountant,
keeping track of your budget,
you bought 45 raspberry pies
for bigger sets of data.
Like websites might have companies,
even network Chuck coffee.
They won't store these in Excel.
They'll store them inside a database
which will function very similarly to an
Excel spreadsheet. Cuz we're still working
with this, which we'll call a table,
but we might need more than one
and we might need a lot more data.
So in my network, Chuck coffee database,
I might have three Excel spreadsheets or
three tables, one for all my customers,
which did you know that Marvel
characters love my coffee.
Thor can't get enough of
the help desk. He loves it.
And they don't have a table
of all the coffees I offer.
And then of course an order table
tracking all the orders that are placed.
And this is a very, very small abbreviated
example of all the data. My network,
Chuck coffee database might
have, which it does have.
So the takeaway here is that databases
are used to store large amounts of data,
data that Karen and her spreadsheet
in Excel couldn't even dream about.
Now these databases, they need a manager.
They need someone to control them,
to get them in line cuz they can act
pretty crazy if they don't have someone
watching him. That's why we have DBMS
at David Bumble management system. No,
I'm just kidding. I pick out him
a lot in this video. Love you.
David DBMS stands for database management
system and actually you probably heard
of a few of them. Microsoft SQL
server, my SQL or I'm sorry,
my SQL that post gray SQL. Am I saying
that right? I don't know Oracle.
There's a lot out there, but just
know that whatever DBMS you choose,
whether it be my SQL, SQL Oracle,
whatever their job is to manage your
databases. They will have different ways.
They do that. But they're
all going to use sequel.
The structured query Lang I can't
even say it structured query language.
There we go. 10 times fast on that one.
This is actually a standard that's
been ratified by the ISO ISO.
So if you learn SQL,
you can pretty much approach most
databases with relative ease.
Now there are some nuances,
some differences going from
like Microsoft SQL to my SQL,
but it's nothing you can't Google. As
long as you understand the concepts. Now,
just so you know, we're going to
create these three databases ourselves.
We're gonna install one and
actually make it happen with my,
but before we do that, there
are two database types.
You have to know about this one. We're
talking about here. This is a relational.
Database. You might see
it abbreviated as R D BMS.
And they by far are the most
popular. It's what I drew out here.
And what makes it relational is these
tables here are kind of like they're
related they're cousins or brothers.
I don't know they're in the family.
And what I mean is like when in
this table here on my orders table,
it says for order 0, 0 1, the coffee
was one. And you're like, what is,
what does that mean? Well, it's actually
tying back to the coffee database.
And then when it says customer
is three, you probably guessed,
it's looking back at the
customer database saying, Hey,
Tony stark ordered the default route.
He loves that stuff. Now again,
we're gonna zero in on
the relational database.
But the other type you wanna
know about is the non relational.
This one doesn't have any family
or any friends. He's very sad.
We're not gonna cover what it is here.
But one type or one DBMS you
might hear about is no sequel,
which fire ship did a
great joke on Twitter.
When I asked you guys if you know SQL
well plate, sir, but a non relational.
It's not like this. It's not related.
It's kind of unstructured data.
And it definitely has
its use case and purpose,
but we're not gonna cover that right
here. Okay. Enough about databases.
Let's actually make one right now. It's
completely free and completely fun.
Now here's what you need.
You won't need much,
pretty much any computer
<laugh> that's it.
We're gonna be playing
with my sequel or my SQL.
And you can pretty much install that
anywhere for free, including windows.
Now I will be walking you through Linux
because I love Linux and it's so easy.
So if you wanna follow along
with me exactly from the
beginning, from the start,
I'm gonna be running the latest version
of a BTU desktop inside a virtual box
VM. If you're like, wait,
what what's he doing?
I've got a video right here on how to
set up virtual machines and what they are
and why they're incredible. You should
go watch that if you haven't already.
And it's completely free to run
this and yeah, that's it. Oh,
I forgot you need coffee
because everything in it,
it requires coffee never checked
out coffee. So here in new BTU,
we're going to launch our terminal first.
Like always we'll get
our repositories updated,
pseudo PT update and quick sip of
coffee while it does its thing.
Next we'll install SQL server with
one command pseudo P T install.
My SQL dash server.
We'll do a tick Y at
the end and that's it.
It'll take just a few moments and
perfect time for a, a coffee break.
We can never have too
much. Now at this point,
you're pretty much running my SQL.
Let's verify it real quick though.
Let's make sure the service is up and
running. We'll do a pseudo system,
CTL status. My SQL and fingers crossed.
You should see active and running.
That means it's healthy. Good to go.
And just hit hu to get outta there. Now
go ahead and play with your database.
Just go crazy. <laugh> you're like,
wait, where is it? <laugh> to access it.
All you have to do is type
in my sequel. That's it.
Well not it you're gonna
have to do pseudo my SQL.
Let's try it now. Yeah. We're
there. Look at, look at that.
We got a nice little, my SQL command
prompt down here. Just waiting for us.
The cur is blinking. Ready
to go. Now just so you know,
the command mind without any parameters
at all worked for us because we're
connecting to our local host.
It also worked because we
don't have a password set,
which is fine for us as
we're just playing around.
But often you might see something
like this, specifying a username,
a remote server.
You wanna connect to the port and
then saying dash P for password.
But we don't have to do that here.
So we're not gonna worry about it.
So here in SQL, let's get the lay of the
land first. What's happening right now.
We're first do a show databases command.
Now just know every time you
type a command at my SQL,
you have to end it with a
semicolon. Otherwise it's like what?
You're not done yet. Come
on. So do that and boom,
some good old default databases.
What do you say? We create our own.
Let's do that right now. We'll create
the database for a network. Chuck coffee.
This one's very hard. I'm just
kidding. It's gonna be so easy.
Simply type in create database.
The name of your database,
which will name N C underscore coffee and
then semicolon. That's it done?
<laugh> and how hard was that? Right?
You just created a database.
That's awesome. If we do
show databases once more,
there it is our very own database, but
he's just sitting there doing nothing.
He's got nothing going on. Let's change
that now to play with our database,
to do things with it, to use it.
We're gonna type in the command use and
then the name of our database and see
underscore coffee semicolon.
And that's it. Database change.
Now we're interacting with that guy
right now. Now remember a database.
We'll have a bunch of tables
assuming you created them,
but right now ours won't have
any and I can prove it to you.
Let's type in the command
show tables with a semicolon
empty set, nothing there.
So let's change that.
Let's create our first table and this
is so cool. This is gonna be fun.
The first table we'll create
is our coffee table. But, um,
and right now I want you to just ignore
the rose. Don't worry about the rose,
the, the data. All right here, all I
want you to focus on are the columns ID,
name, and region and roast. We're
gonna deal with that right now.
So to create a table, we're gonna
type in create table crazy. Right?
And then right after that, we'll name
our table. Of course we gotta name it.
Coffee table. Don't wanna
miss that opportunity.
And then right after that,
we'll do an open parenthesis
and go ahead and hit enter it.
It'll be fine because we
didn't put a semicolon.
Semicolon means you're done doing
anything else means like I'm not done yet.
That's that's what it means. Now
here, inside these parentheses,
we'll be defining our columns. What we
saw before ID name, blah, blah. You know,
you got it. So our first column will
simply call ID. And then right after that,
I'm gonna type in I N T no. What
is that? So here with our column,
we're defining the name of a
column, that guy right there,
but then we also have to define what type
of data is gonna be in that column or
in the rows that we're gonna
have underneath it here.
We're saying we want it to
be an integer or a number.
That's the type of data that
we'll live in that column.
And that's pretty much all there is to it.
We'll type in a column
to tell them that, Hey,
we're not done with our
columns just yet hit enter.
Our next column will be name.
And then we'll define what type of
data we want inside that column here.
I'm gonna type in V R C H
a R or variable character,
which is an end determinant length
string data type. <laugh> basically,
it's just letters <laugh>
and stuff. It's a string.
I can also define how long I want that
to be how many characters are allowed.
So I'll just say 255 and parentheses
just like that. And let's keep going.
Comma, next thing or column it was region.
This will also be a string
or variable character.
It'll keep going until we're done.
Oh, we'll have one more roast.
Now my last column here, I'm
not going to add a comma.
You only add a comma when you're
saying, Hey, I have more to say,
we don't have more to say
we're done. I'll hit enter.
I'll do a closing parenthesis.
And then to end our command
like we do in all my SQL stuff,
we're gonna type in a
semicolon. That's it.
We're about to create our first table
and set our database. Ready? Set, enter,
go. Let's take a look at it. Show tables.
There it is. There's our coffee table.
Now that's just the name
of it. What do you say?
We look inside and see the
actual columns we made.
We can type in and describe coffee
table. And that'll give us some more
info. We got our field and our type,
and we'll cover more on this stuff
here in a minute on, by the way,
when we're defining our table and
defining that columns and everything,
the fields that's part of
defining our schema or how our
databases are arranged and, and organized.
We're not gonna go too deep into that.
Just know that when people say schema,
that's pretty much what they mean. Now
there's nothing on our coffee table.
Let's ask some stuff to it,
looking at our database,
let's add the default route.
Let's insert a row into our table
and my sequel we'll type in insert
in two. And then we'll specify
our table, which was coffee table.
Then we'll say, here are the
values. We'll actually use the word,
the command values. And we'll define
our values inside parentheses.
The first one's an en integer, and
I'm just gonna put it in as one.
That's the first ID. Second one was name,
which will be a string
default wrap. Then origin,
Ethiopia, also a string and
finally roast, which was light.
So what's happening here. We
have the insert into command.
So we're telling my sequel,
we're inserting into <laugh>
the coffee table table.
And it's like, what are you inserting?
Well, here are our values, bam.
And notice we're going in order of
our columns. And we have to do that.
Got the ID, the name, the region,
and the roast. Then once we're done,
what do we do?
We type in semicolon to say
we are done and awesome.
Now what I love about my SQL and most
SQL things is, uh, it'll tell us, Hey,
the query it's okay.
We got this. It's good.
And it tells us there was one
row affected, which row? Well,
the one we just added now,
I know you want to see that data
inside your database, but so far,
I haven't shown you how to do that.
Cause if we do show tables
or describe coffee table,
it doesn't show us the data inside yet.
So I guess I can go ahead and show you
your first select statement. Um, ah,
should I wait? Yeah, no, let's do
it right now. I know you can't wait.
<laugh> so here's how we
look inside of our table.
Let's pull some data out of
there. We'll type in select.
We'll do an asterisk and I'll
explain this here in a second.
And we'll say from our table
coffee table semicolon.
Now what's happening here. We're telling
my sequel, I wanna select some data.
And it's like, well, what
data from what column?
And we're saying all of it
<laugh> I want everything.
That's what the asterisk means. And then
it's like, okay, fine. From what table?
Where are you getting this from? Well,
we're getting it from our coffee table.
I wanna see my coffee stuff. And
that's what we're doing here.
It's a very basic select statement.
You'll see this one all the time.
But if you just wanna pull all the info
from a table, that's how you do it.
Let's take a look. There it is. How
cool is that? So if you just did this
clap, pat yourself on the back, that's
a big deal. You created a database,
you created a table inside the database
and you added some data to it, simple,
but killer. Now here's
a challenge for you.
What I want you to do is fill
out the rest of this database,
all the rest of our coffees. Go ahead
and pause the video. Pause, UN pause.
Let's see how you did. Let's do
our select statement once more,
select everything from coffee table
and we should see a lot more things.
<laugh> yes, it's so nice and neat.
I love it. If yours looks like
this, congrats, that's awesome. Now,
another challenge for you.
I want you to select only the names
of the coffee from that table.
That's all I wanna see. Can you
do that? Let's try it out. Select,
instead of saying everything,
let's just select the
name from coffee table.
Bam just got the names
of our coffee. That's it.
Now here's the next challenge for you.
I want you to create our next
table and do this by yourself.
I'm not gonna show you,
create our customer table with all of
our Marvel customers and also name your
table. Avengers, just like
this. Okay? Pause the video. Go
and pause. Let's see
how you did now. Again,
I wanted you to create this table and
if you haven't already go ahead and fill
it out with all this information.
It'll take about two minutes,
but it gives you practice. But if you
did it right, it should look like this.
Let's go ahead and select
everything from that table.
Select all columns from Avengers.
Let's see how it looks.
<laugh> oh, nice. Clean,
tidy data. I love it. Now here
with our Marvel characters,
let me show you some of the power <laugh>
of SQL and how we can find or query
our data. So let's try this.
Let's do a select statement,
just like we did before
everything from Avengers.
But let's say we only wanna see
the Avengers that are from earth.
That's all we wanna see. How
do we do that with where? No,
I'm not losing my mind.
<laugh> watch this.
I can add another filter saying
where origin equals the string
earth semicolon. So let's break it down.
I'm selecting all columns
from the table, Avengers,
but I only wanna see where the
column origin equals earth.
That's it let's see what happens. Bam.
I only got the earthlings, check it out.
<laugh> isn't that cool though.
If you had a large amount of data,
being able to just select, pinpoint
the data you want, like that is killer.
And that's just a basic SQL statement.
Let me show you a few more quick ones.
Let's pull up that same statement.
Let's say we wanted to see all the
Avengers from earth and Asguard how
we do that. It's pretty simple. Actually.
All I have to do is add one more
filter to it. I'll just say, or, or,
or a G equals Asgard.
So my filter says, Hey,
origin can be earth or,
or origin can be Asgard.
Let's see what happens. Bam. Just
add a Thor. Let's try this one.
Maybe I wanna see all the Avengers that
are under the age of 30. Let's try that.
In fact, actually pause the video. See
if you can do this pause, UN pause.
We'll select the alias
column from a vendors where
age is less than 30.
We can do stuff like that.
Bam. How cool is that?
I just got the aliases
Spider-Man and well tree.
And that's pretty much an endless
combination of how you can filter things.
I can say where not origin equals earth.
I wanna see everyone. That's not
from earth using our not statement.
So you can go crazy with queries.
And often you may be typing in a terminal
doing these queries, or it could be a,
a gooey application or it's programmatic.
You're programming things in Python to
search for data with queries like this.
It's super powerful. Now so far, I've
shown you how to add data to a table,
but what if you wanna remove stuff?
Cuz did you notice this? Look at this.
Some dude named Jeff snuck into
my table. He's not in Avenger.
How do you even get in there? So real
quick, um, go ahead and add Jeff,
add this data to your table
and then let's remove him.
So pause the video real quick,
Adam, and then let's remove him.
We can remove the records from our
tables, with the delete command.
We'll say delete from we'll specify
our table Avengers and we'll tell them
what we're wanting to delete. We could
delete a lot of things all at once.
Gotta be careful, but all
we care about is Jeff.
So we'll say where we'll
use our filtering again,
where we'll say first name equals Jeff.
That should do it. That should take
out Jeff goodbye. Jeff. And he is gone.
I think let's do our select statement
once more. Woo. Okay. Jeff is gone.
Now we can also update these
stuff in our table. For example,
I was informed of this grot. Doesn't have
a last name. Let's just Groot my bad.
So let's change that.
Let's delete that we can update entries
in our table with the update command.
We're gonna update Avengers and
we'll use the set command to set a
certain column equal to something.
So we'll set last name
equal to null, to nothing.
That's how we do that empty.
And because we don't wanna set every last
name to Noel will say where first name
equals group. That should do it. Let's
try it out. Awesome. So actually I,
I didn't test this before. I wanna
make sure it works. Excellent.
GT is now accurate and you guys
can stop yelling at me. Now,
last thing on this before
we get kind of crazy,
let's go ahead and select
all the Avengers. Once more,
all the columns let's say we wanna
see them in order of their age,
youngest to oldest, let's see that
we can do that by typing in order,
by the column age. And we'll say, because
we're going from younger to older,
it'll be ascending. So we'll do a S C
let's try it out. Perfect. Look at that.
17, 18 35 to 42 5000. That's a
big jump. Let's do it in reverse.
Let's do oldest to youngest. We'll
change that to D S or <laugh> sorry.
D E S C descending. Awesome. Okay.
Last thing I'm gonna show you.
Maybe I, I might get too excited and
show you something else, but we'll see.
Okay. Let's try this right now.
Our tables looking pretty amazing.
All the Avengers are here.
Well, some of them, well,
let's say we wanna know
one more thing about them.
I wanna know if they have a beard, so
it'll be beard. It'll be yes or no.
We're actually true or false. Let's do
that. So here in our database, our table,
we're gonna alter the table to have
another column after it's already created.
Let's do it right now. Pretty simple.
Actually the command is alter.
We wanna alter it. We gotta
tell SQL what we wanna alter.
We're gonna alter a table,
specifically the Avenger table.
We're going to add a new
column. We'll name it, beard.
And then we'll tell it what type of data
it's going to be now because I want it
to be true. False. I'm gonna type in
bullion. Cuz bullion is true or false.
That's a special data type.
So here we're telling SQL we wanna alter
the table of vendors and the way we're
altering it is by adding the column,
beard with the ion data
type at enter done.
Now let's select and see
what it looks like right now.
<laugh> look at that new
information, new column.
Now here's a challenge for you.
I want you to go in and update the record
for the beard column for each of these
Avengers, whether or not
they have a beard, you should
know that already. Right?
So go ahead and do it real
quick. Pause the video on pause.
Here's how you would do that. Like we
just covered with the update command.
We'll update the table of Avengers.
We'll set beard equal to
true where let's just say
first name equals Thor. Cuz
we know a Thor has a beard.
Bam. Let's see what happens. Perfect.
And for group, he doesn't have a beard.
So we'll set beard to false
where first name equals groups.
Let's see what happened.
Noticing that one is true.
Zero is false. Okay, we're gonna
stop here. I could keep going.
There are things I have not covered, but
I don't wanna make this video too long.
But I hope in this video I gave you
enough to make you like feel semi
CT. Like I know what a database is.
I create one. I can select things,
but also I wanna give you that hunger
that drive to learn just a bit more,
go beyond what I'm showing you here
because there are things I didn't cover.
Like look here. We did build these
two tables inside our database,
but we never built the orders table.
And more importantly, we never.
Built the relationships
between all these tables,
which would involve making the
ID field of both our customers,
our Avengers and our
coffee, the primary key.
And then when we reference
those fields in our order table,
those will be foreign keys.
And that unlocks the full
power of relational databases,
allowing us to do things like
joins and creating views,
which basically is pulling data from
all these tables and only seeing what we
want to see, like how many times
does Spider-Man order the dark roast.
We could find stuff like that.
So I'm not gonna cover that here.
If you want me to create a video on
that, let me know below. But anyways,
that's all I got for today.
Thank you for taking some time to have
some coffee with me and talk about SQL or
SQL. Well.